<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Unofficial UCSC Student Guide – Off Campus Housing</title><link>https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/</link><description>Recent content in Off Campus Housing on Unofficial UCSC Student Guide</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: House/Apartment</title><link>https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/house_apartment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/house_apartment/</guid><description>
&lt;p>I got a house close to the base of campus in Summer 2020 and this is an approximate sequence of events and resources I found (but not necessarily used) to help get a place to live.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="picking-your-group">Picking Your Group&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://communityrentals.ucsc.edu/renters/before-you-rent/index.html">UCSC Community Rentals - Before You Rent&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most important thing I would do before even starting to look for a house is to find a solid group of people to live with. Personally, I think a group of 3 - 5 people is a great middle ground for house cleanliness and fun but also somewhat private and quiet to study. Make sure you talk about everyone&amp;rsquo;s preferences, living condition/way of living, and price ranges. It is very competitive to find housing in Santa Cruz, so you want to pick a solid group who can communicate and be ready to apply to maximize chances of getting the house. You should be doing this around February.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="starting-your-search">Starting Your Search&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>After you have your group picked out, have everyone in the group start searching any and all websites for house listings that match the group&amp;rsquo;s preferences, while simulateously filling out a &lt;a href="https://communityrentals.ucsc.edu/renters/before-you-rent/rental-application-packet.html">renter&amp;rsquo;s application packet&lt;/a>. Some landlords ask for it and some don&amp;rsquo;t, but it takes a little while to put together, so start early. See the link above for more information on it. This also the time to take the quick &lt;a href="https://communityrentals.ucsc.edu/renters-workshop/index.html">Canvas Renter&amp;rsquo;s Workshop&lt;/a>. Some landlords ask that you complete it and show the certificate of completion (mine did), but even if they don&amp;rsquo;t ask, there is still some good information in there about off campus housing in general. You should be doing this in February - March.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links-for-your-search">Links for Your Search&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here is a list of sites to search for (in no particular order, not exhaustive):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.zillow.com/">Zillow&lt;/a> (this is where I found my house)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.apartments.com/">Apartments.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.realtor.com/rentals">Realtor.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://monterey.craigslist.org/">Craigslist&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/1454999854729837">Santa Cruz Housing Facebook Public Group&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/ucscunofficialhousing/">UCSC Housing, Sublets &amp;amp; Roommates Facebook Private Group&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/1450196305292286/">University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) Housing, Sublets &amp;amp; Roommates Facebook Private Group&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="contacting-potential-landlords">Contacting Potential Landlords&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Keep searching all the sites you can and when you reach out to landlord via email or text (however they prefer), I would recommend only having one person communicating with the landlord and then they will convey the updates to the rest of the group - it is usually much more oragnized and less confusing to keep track of who is talking to who. You should be doing this starting in March - April.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you first contact a landlord to express interest in their listing, I recommend you do the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>quickly introduce yourself and your group - names, majors, year&lt;/li>
&lt;li>express interest in that specific listing - give the address of the place so they know which one in case they have more than one&lt;/li>
&lt;li>try to sell yourself and your group a little - make yourselves sound like good tenants (and make sure that is the reality too)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ask about availability for a tour, applying, and signing the lease so they can get a feel that you are serious about securing this house.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Keep this initial email/text with the landlord SHORT. Get to the point - housing is competitive in Santa Cruz, so you don&amp;rsquo;t want to deter landlords with a long essay. Make it easier for them.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: This process of searching for potential houses and contacting landlords usually takes a while, so be patient and keep searching. Many landlords will ghost you, leave you on read, or take a while to reply. Don&amp;rsquo;t take it personal and just move on to the next.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Pay attention to the date the house is available for new tenants if it is mentioned in the listing online. If it isn&amp;rsquo;t online you can ask about it in the initial email, but it will be in the lease. I prefer a start date/time that is anytime outside the school year in case my group doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to resign for another year or we get kicked out, we won&amp;rsquo;t be doing this whole process again while taking classes. Most leases are 12 months long, so you will be paying for the summer months rent anyway, but you can ask for a month to month lease or a term shorter than 12 months (although landlords do not prefer this).&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="reading-the-lease">Reading the Lease&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>After engaging in talks with landlord and you seem to have a place that will be yours, the landlord will send you the lease and give you a little bit of time to read and sign it. Please read the lease completely.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: Look for contradictions, unfair rules, things that stand out or don&amp;rsquo;t make sense, and ask for clarification. Make sure you, your group, and the landlord are all in agreement about the terms of the lease BEFORE signing. If you don&amp;rsquo;t read the whole thing, then at the very least, read the first couple pages since that is where the main points are usually.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="move-in-and-things-to-set-up">Move In and Things to Set Up&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Next is to pay your (refundable) safety deposit, get the keys, and move in! Congratulations! Some houses are prefunished, but I would say most are not. So figure out if anything comes with the house and fill in the missing furniture or appliances with your group.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Read the terms of your lease to remember what utilities (PG&amp;amp;E, water, trash, cable/internet) you are and not responsible for paying and get those set up. I would say that usually one person takes responsiblilty to pay for one utility to make it fair and everyone pays them back.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: start setting up the utilities (especially internet) as soon as you get the keys to make sure you have a smooth start.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Be a good housemate, roommate, neighbor, and tenant. It isn&amp;rsquo;t technically your house, but you should be treating as if it is (or risk losing a lot of your safety deposit)!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="more-resources">More resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://communityrentals.ucsc.edu/">Community Rentals&lt;/a> - (ucsc site) has many more links and resources to help&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.places4students.com/Places/School?SchoolID=%2f7UnHPDakTw%3d">Places4Students&lt;/a> - place to find rentals and housemates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://deanofstudents.ucsc.edu/basic-needs/off-campus-housing-legal-services.html">Legal Services &amp;amp; Consulation&lt;/a> - free access to an attorney for UCSC students if you have legal concerns regarding off campus housing (offered via UCSC Dean of Students)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://communityrentals.ucsc.edu/renters/before-you-rent/questions-to-ask.html">Community Rentals - Questions to Ask&lt;/a> - questions to ask the landlord&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Docs: University Town Center</title><link>https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/utc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hilalmorrar.com/ucsc-guide/docs/housing/offcampus/utc/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>